In this lesson we're going to be focusing on generic functions and TypeScript.
To generic functions, let us write, file-exable and reusable functions while still keeping
full-type safety.
And you're going to use this whenever you might want to be tempted to reach for the keyword
any but felt uncomfortable doing so.
So imagine for example we have a function, and our function of identity, and we want to supply
it any value, any type, might simply do return the value and let's do return value.
Now this works, but TypeScript's going to lose all the information about this value
is type. So if it returns a string, TypeScript doesn't even know that anymore.
And this is where we're going to introduce or have a generic function, which allows us
to define a placeholder for any type.
And we do that by using the angle, and then T. This is going to basically the format
or to finding a generic type. Let's now turn our function, our same identity function
into a generic function, so function_identity, that's the same.
And now we actually do angle brackets T, and then our brackets for our parameters, so value,
and we say the value, rather than any is now of this generic type T. The function can
also return any type or our typed generic type, so that's also our type T.
Because we have a type T, this means that our parameter and our return type, both the
same type of T. Now we just return our value, and that's our generic function.
And let's see how that works. Let's say we have const num, for numbers, we call our
identity function, and we need to find the actual type that wants here to be. So we want
it to be a number in this case. We put number in brackets, angle brackets, and then we can
define the actual parameters. And notice that TypeScript is now prompting us for the value
as a number, because we defined it here. Now you can just do 10, let's go into return
us, an integer of number. But let's say we want to now pass its string, rather than
a number, we can do const text equals identity again, and in angle brackets, we're going
to say the type of string. And now look, what TypeScript does, it then prompts us for the
value as a string, we do hello, and it's going to go into return a string. So you can
immediately see that although this looks quite complicated here, it actually is quite straightforward
by just finding the type we want inside the angle brackets here. We could also use inference
as well. So if we did, for example, rather than string, we just remove string from here,
TypeScripts can be smart enough to understand that it's because we're by supplying a string
here, that we are dealing with strings. And if I then change it to say a number, like
10, again, it then knows that this is going to be a number that's coming out of it.
We could also use our function for doing things as an array. So let's say, for example,
we've got a function like this, and a function getverse, and going to use our t again,
but we're going to this time supply an array of generic t's types to do t, but we can now
do a two square brackets after it. So we have an array of type t. Our function is going
to return t. This is to return an array. And now we can do our array of first elements
by doing our ar.0. Now we can call our get first function, and we can supply an array
like 123. And that, of course, will return one. We could do gets first, and then maybe
do an array of strings, like one, doing three, or whatever, one and two. And it's going
to return the very first one of that array. But a generic function can also contain more
than one type. We've only got one in this particular example. So let's do another function,
and we're going to now have two types. So how do we do that? We have function, so pair,
we have letter t. And now by convention, the second word to the y is u, but that's by convention.
Let's do that. Now we have our first parameter is of type t. And our second parameter
is of type u. And then we can simply return an array. So we can return if first and the
second as an array. Let's now try and use this function to might do something like pair.
And we pair maybe one, say an integer, and maybe apple. So it doesn't have to be the same
type. We could have, again, a number and a string like we have here. It could be two numbers
could be two strings. But each of the type parameters is then tracked independently. But
let's actually try and put that into some context by doing a real word example. So we're
going to have another function here. We're going to call it fetch data, like an API,
a generic type t. The data is going to be of type t. And this is going to return a promise.
A promise, the promise is going to return type t. Now we do return promise resolve, right?
And then we're going to take resolve our data. And this is a very common practice when
working with APIs.